<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Projects | I'm Brian Chu]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.brianchu.com/blog/categories/projects/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.brianchu.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-29T07:13:03-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.brianchu.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brian Chu]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My First iPhone Game: Devils in Heaven]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.brianchu.com/blog/2013/11/20/my-first-iphone-game-devils-in-heaven/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-20T10:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.brianchu.com/blog/2013/11/20/my-first-iphone-game-devils-in-heaven</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Introducing my first iPhone game, <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/devils-in-heaven/id744368918?mt=8&amp;uo=4&amp;at=10lpgg">Devils in Heaven</a>, a 2D infinite runner game with interactive obstacles!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/devils-in-heaven/id744368918?mt=8&amp;uo=4&amp;at=10lpgg"><img class="center" src="/images/app_store_download.png"></a></p>

<p><img class="img-thumbnail center" src="/images/blog/2013/dih-animated.gif" title="&lsquo;Devils in Heaven&rsquo; &lsquo;Video of gameplay.&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>Beezlebubbly is stuck in heaven, and you need to help him escape from the not-too-happy angels chasing him. Fling statues and harps around and protect Beezlebubbly from the arrows.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s completely free with no ads or in-app purchases, though I might add in-app purchases if the game gets popular enough.</p>

<p>Like it? <a href="https://www.makegameswith.us/games/devils-in-heaven/">Text a link to your friends!</a></p>

<p>Built with <a href="http://www.cocos2d-iphone.org/">coocs2d-iphone</a> and <a href="http://www.kobold2d.com/display/KKSITE/Home">Kobold2D</a>. Published by <a href="https://www.makegameswith.us/">MakeGamesWithUs</a>.</p>

<p><img class="img-thumbnail center" src="/images/blog/2013/dih-screenshot1.png" title="&lsquo;Devils in Heaven&rsquo; &lsquo;Screenshot of gameplay.&rsquo;" ></p>

<h1>The Process</h1>

<p>Originally the game was meant to be titled <em>Demolition Gauntlet</em> &ndash; featuring a knight running through Hell, chased by demons and devils. That was a pretty uninspiring theme, so I inverted the concept, giving the game the whimsical twist I wanted it to have from the start.</p>

<p>Devils in Heaven was a project I worked on in short bursts, a project that I left dormant for months at a time. I started the game in June of 2012 when I interned over the summer with MakeGamesWithUs (MGWU) after high school. The internship program, which continues today, is unlike your typical internship &ndash; it&rsquo;s more like an incubator where you work on our own game alongside the MGWU developers and other interns. Over three months I finished roughly half the game &ndash; while learning Objective-C and cocos2d.</p>

<p>Afterwards, I <a href="/about">joined</a> the MGWU team full-time as I took a full year off from school. I worked on the game here and there, bringing it up to 90%, before largely shelving the project for nearly a year until the past few weeks.</p>

<p><img class="img-thumbnail center" src="/images/blog/2013/dih-githistory.jpg" title="&lsquo;Git commit history&rsquo; &lsquo;Git commit history from August 2012 to November 2013&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>There were a couple of difficult challenges. The game features ragdoll physics for the devil and angels, and setting up the parameters for the physical bodies was quite a lot of work. Dealing with physics in general was challenging at times: all the objects in the game are objects that can fully interact with the physical world, which meant dealing with unexpected behavior like being tipped over.</p>

<p>One cool part: I got to use some of the physics I learned in school when I was calculating the velocity of the arrows in the game, using the kinematic equations of motion.</p>

<p><img class="img-thumbnail center" src="/images/blog/2013/dih-equations-small.jpg" title="&lsquo;Kinematic equations&rsquo; &lsquo;Handwritten calulations of the arrow&rsquo;s velocity using kinematic equations.&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>The project was the first 10,000+ lines of code, object-oriented program I ever worked on, and it shows &ndash; the code is in dire need of serious refactoring, probably a month&rsquo;s worth of work. My first target? The entire class inheritance and object protocol (interface) system. The OOP structure that I originally created in the game over a year ago is convoluted, tightly coupled, and distinctly non-modular.</p>

<p>But it works! Hope you like it!</p>

<p><img class="img-thumbnail center" src="/images/blog/2013/dih-physics.png" title="&lsquo;Physics debugging&rsquo; &lsquo;Screenshot of game with physics debugging graphics.&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>By the way, I&rsquo;m looking for a summer internship! So <a href="#" data-toggle="modal" data-target=".contact-modal.hide.fade">contact me</a>!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
