<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Life | I'm Brian Chu]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.brianchu.com/blog/categories/life/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.brianchu.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-30T00:07:56-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.brianchu.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brian Chu]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Making Decisions]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.brianchu.com/blog/2014/03/28/making-decisions/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-28T08:22:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.brianchu.com/blog/2014/03/28/making-decisions</id>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="article-cover top-bottom-border" style="background-image: url('/images/blog/2014/decision-frameworks.jpg')"></div>

A few of the frameworks and factors I've encountered for thinking about the decisions and choices I make.

<!-- more -->

When facing multiple priorities and opportunities that you can take, consider these ideas:

1. **The regret-minimization framework:** Ask yourself which opportunity you will regret not taking. Ask yourself if you will regret doing something. This has probably been the most influential for me. <a name="1-back" href="#1">[1]</a>.

    Regret-minimization often helps me think about action versus inaction and risk versus safety. This can be mundane: should you go out to eat with friends or stay inside and eat by yourself? This can be a major life change: would you regret having worked at a startup? Or would you regret having stayed at a stable company? The answers to these questions can change depending on where you are in life. There are cases where you truly might regret going to a startup.

2. **Focus on optimizing a single factor and only then seek ways to mitigate the tradeoffs.** We tend to evaluate choices based on tradeoffs. <a name="2-back" href="#2">[2]</a>

    For example, an engineer friend of mine was trying to decide on which company to join. He felt that joining a rapidly growing startup would maximize his potential upside (through equity), whereas joining a big tech firm would give him the opportunity to learn more, earn him more money (expected value), and boost his resume. Staying at his current company would increase his opportunities for internal advancement. Under this framework, he should examine the most important factor (pick one of: education, salary, upside potential, advancement) to optimize, and ignore all other factors. This is useful because the most distracting part of making a decision is having to consider all of the tiny little tradeoffs that have to be evaluated.

3. **Consider which choices are time-dependent.**

    Some opportunities can only be seized now. An example would be a job offer about to expire. A subtler category of opportunities consists of opportunities that are *better* taken now, rather than later. For example, traveling is usually done better when you're younger, because more activities and more social circles are open to you. But you can travel any time you're physically fit. Similarly, attending college is usually better done when you're younger, because of the people you meet and friendships you form, but you could still attend college at any point in life. Then there are opportunities that you have years and years to pursue in the future, like writing a book.

4. **Consider your comparative advantages.** Which opportunities are specific to your skills, and which are general opportunities open to all? You're going to have a better chance of success pursuing an opportunity that suits your skills. I wrote more about this [in a previous blog post](/blog/2014/01/27/work-where-you-have-comparative-advantages/).

5. **Potential is greater than what is possible right now.** I try to refrain from judging opportunities by what they mean today. Judge them by what they mean for the future. This is more specifically geared towards technological opportunities.

    A relevant example is the recent trend of cryptocurrencies and Bitcoin. I personally don't find Bitcoin to be very useful. I think it's very flawed, and I've observed that most applications of cryptocurrencies seem like the result of engineers trying to come up with ideas for Bitcoin, rather than trying to solve actual problems with Bitcoin. But I try to stop myself from dismissing cryptocurrencies out of hand, simply because most flaws of cyptocurrencies are only flaws that exist today. They're implementation flaws, not necessarily inherent flaws. These flaws might be eliminated in the future. A better cryptocurrency might arise. Better exchanges might arise. Brilliant and obviously useful applications of cryptocurrencies might arise. Potential is greater than what is possible today.

These are just ways of thinking about decisions, not hard rules on how to act. I don't always follow these frameworks myself. Often these frameworks don't apply. Sometimes they might even conflict!

<a name="1" href="#1-back">[1]</a> I encountered this in an [interview of Jeff Bezos](http://www.achievement.org/autodoc/page/bez0int-3).

<a name="2" href="#2-back">[2]</a> This was a piece of advice I read online, but I forget where I found it.]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Work where you have comparative advantages]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.brianchu.com/blog/2014/01/27/work-where-you-have-comparative-advantages/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-27T10:30:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.brianchu.com/blog/2014/01/27/work-where-you-have-comparative-advantages</id>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="article-cover" style="background-image: url('/images/blog/2014/comparative-advantage.jpg')"></div>

Like most developers, you probably keep a running list of ideas for apps you might build. I do. They all seem promising and potentially useful. How do you prioritize what to build? One way I try to decide what to work on: I think of my comparative advantages.

<!-- more -->

Work where you have a comparative advantage. Consider the unique skills, insights, networks of people, networks of beta users, and marketing channels that are available to you as a result of your where you are today and what you've done in the past. What you choose to work on should take advantage of those things <a name="1-back" href="#1">[1]</a>.

College students, like myself, will probably have greater insight into the social behavior of teenagers and twenty-somethings than other demographics <a name="2-back" href="#2">[2]</a>. They have access to an extremely broad and dense group of fellow students, all close to their age. They have access to college-specific activities - dorm life, taking classes, parties, homework - and close access to a set of potential beta users in a narrow demographic, other students. A college student can access a huge variety of college-specific marketing channels - friends, clubs, campus billboards, club tabling, and classes. An experienced engineer will have a different set comparative advantages. An engineer might have insight into the problems companies face with software architecture, databases, servers, testing. An engineer will have access to a strong network of engineers, managers, and CTOs. An engineer might have better access to other marketing channels - meetups, invite-only networking events, and technology conferences.

Domain expertise is a subset of comparative advantage. A college student would be hard-pressed to build a better CRM that takes the market. They don't have domain expertise. On the other hand, an operations leader with years of enterprise experience would be hard-pressed to build the next trendy social networking app. They don't have any domain expertise. They don't necessarily suffer from handicaps; they just don't have any legs up on the competition - twenty-somethings with the same ideas. So they would be better off competing elsewhere and exploiting their own comparative advantages.

Take a moment to think: what are your comparative advantages? What networks do you have access to, both as a result of your location and your experience? What skills do you have? What kind of beta users can you test your projects with? What insights do you have as a result of your experience? What other distribution/marketing channels do you have?

I'm in college right now (after a hiatus). That's why my latest side project is tackling the problem of buying and selling things locally - a quintessentially college student problem.

*A cautionary note*: This is only one way to think about choosing your work. Working where you have comparative advantages can sometimes conflict with other valuable goals. Examples include: trying becoming well-rounded, trying to change careers, and trying to learn about new technologies. In those cases you have to take other factors into account!

<a name="1" href="#1-back">[1]</a> I don't use the term as precisely as it's used in economics. Technically, comparative advantage is the idea that economies are better at producing different goods. Perhaps China produces cars more efficiently than software. Perhaps America produces software more efficiently than cars. Even if America is more efficient in absolute terms at mass-producing cars than China, the idea behind comparative advantage is that if America focuses on software, China focuses on cars, and both trade with each other, both will be richer than if they didn't focus on their comparative advantages.

<a name="2" href="#2-back">[2]</a> I use the term "probably" very loosely, on the assumption that "you get the point." None of these are absolutes. There are definitely college students who don't know anything about their fellow students. There are definitely people 10 years out of school that have deep insight into teenage social behavior.]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
