<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: life | I'm Brian Chu]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.brianchu.com/blog/categories/life/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.brianchu.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-08-21T01:03:31-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.brianchu.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brian Chu]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why I'm Not Giving What We Can]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.brianchu.com/blog/2015/05/09/why-im-not-giving-what-we-can/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-09T05:47:01-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.brianchu.com/blog/2015/05/09/why-im-not-giving-what-we-can</id>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="article-cover" style="background-image: url('/images/blog/2015/giving-pledge.jpg')"></div>

#### Choosing what to believe

A few friends made the [Giving What We Can](https://www.givingwhatwecan.org/) pledge to donate 10% of their income every year to charity. This sparked an interesting discussion over our reasons for or against making the pledge. Most people against the pledge admitted they were selfish. I argued that by investing in myself I would be in a better position in the future to help the world. That the money would be better spent investing in myself so that I could impact the world later. <!-- more --> This does seem to be a more complicated version of being selfish. I&#8217;ll admit there is a selfish kernel in this belief, but I believe there is more to this belief than just selfishness. The selfish kernel of this idea is in how personal it is.

Objectively, looking at facts and what we empirically know to be true, the most likely outcome of my future is that I&#8217;ll never actually be in this position. I&#8217;ll never be in a position where I can make better use of my money to make the world a better place than a well organized charity can. And so objectively my money would be better spent by following the pledge.

But this reminds me of other areas where what I know objectively is at odds with what I believe subjectively.

I know there is no objective, external, absolute meaning to life (perhaps you know something else) <a name="1-back" href="#1">[1]</a>. But personally - subjectively - I believe I get to decide whatever my life will mean to me. The idea that there is no objective meaning to life is a completely useless thought. Pondering this idea is completely counterproductive.

The fact that I probably won&#8217;t be able to make better use of my money to impact the world is similarly counterproductive. It smacks of a defeatist, self-fulfilling prophecy. The selfish kernel of my reason against pledging is just that - I selfishly do not believe in that idea. Instead, I choose to prefer my biased, personal belief that I can make better use of my money in the future to make the world a better place than any charity can.

I know this is all (logically, objectively) circular. So what?

<a name="1" href="#1-back">[1]</a> Obviously, I&#8217;m not religious.
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Discovery of Magic]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.brianchu.com/blog/2015/03/24/the-discovery-of-magic/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-24T10:00:10-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.brianchu.com/blog/2015/03/24/the-discovery-of-magic</id>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="article-cover" style="background-image: url('/images/blog/2015/discovery-magic.jpg')"></div>

I spend plenty of time thinking about the kinds of questions most ambitious college students do: how should I prepare for the future? What kind of career should I pursue? What&#8217;s worth learning?

<!-- more -->

Most of my college friends plan their next semester, next year, and the year after graduation. Most of my friends in industry plan about as far as their next job. This is a pretty good strategy. I don&#8217;t believe in planning any further out than a couple of years, because I can never predict how things change in my life. The future is hard to predict.

I don&#8217;t mean you shouldn&#8217;t think about the future and have long-term goals. You should have an idea of where you want to be four years from now. Maybe even ten years from now. But you shouldn&#8217;t start from where you want to be four years from now and plan out the steps in between <a name="1-back" href="#1">[1]</a>. The details of the future are hard to predict.

But if it&#8217;s possible to have some idea of where you want to be four years from now, it&#8217;s also possible to have an inkling about the world fifty years from now. We know that the world fifty years from now is going to be completely different. There we have it - we know something. Compare the 1960s to today: a total transformation. In the 1960s the Vietnam War was escalating. Cancer was a death sentence. Colonialism in Africa was still unwinding. ALGOL was just invented. The civil rights movement in America was beginning. <a name="2-back" href="#2">[2]</a>

**Society will change.** Even if you don&#8217;t share my beliefs about the direction of the future, and even though you can never predict how things change in your life, you can predict something: change is coming. Technological change, social change, and economic change. It&#8217;s obvious, but we don&#8217;t think about this much. We usually watch events as they happen, as spectators. Every so often we&#8217;ll stop and realize what happened. So it&#8217;s a useful exercise to think about the future now.

Some specific trends that I believe will play out in my lifetime:

1. **We will discover magic (again).** Life and society will be transformed several times over by advances in science and engineering. I don&#8217;t have a single shred of doubt about this. I can&#8217;t tell you exactly what will change, though, except that they will involve rapidly growing fields like biotech, energy, and computing <a name="3-back" href="#3">[3]</a>. If only to prepare myself, I like to describe the future as having the kind of change we would call magic: sufficiently advanced technology.

2. **We will live drastically longer lives.** As a result of advances in medicine, I will probably live beyond the age of 120.

    And there is some chance I will live to an age beyond 300.

    Historical data actually doesn&#8217;t support this idea - in recent decades life expectancy has only inched up a year or so per decade (roughly one year from 2002-2010 in the US). This is a problem whenever you look at the past and try to use that to look towards a future of what I believe to be accelerating change. I still believe medicine will be one of the fields that is transformed in the next fifty years. The seeds have already been planted in genomics and biotech.

3. **The divide between labor and capital will grow.** During my longer lifespan, those with capital - financial resources, machinery, and organizational clout - will gain a growing and disproportionate share of wealth and power over those with labor - employment and time that people have to put into their work. This is closely related to rising income inequality in America <a name="4-back" href="#4">[4]</a>. This will significantly alter the political landscape of the future.

    We might be tempted to believe this is an trend that we or society will stop through political action. I read an interesting idea on this: with increasing inequality, larger and larger swaths of the populace would be excluded from access to wealth and power. Most modern nations are democracies, so rising inequality might eventually be checked by majority support for redistributive economics policies (heavier taxes on the wealthy, and so on). But I wouldn&#8217;t count on this to let us safely ignore the trend. Inequality will continue increasing for some time. Entrepreneurs and those with capital, expertise, and financial resources will generally emigrate to nations with less economically restrictive policies (more economically liberal policies). And technology is inherently a multiplier on productivity - even if the rising tide of technology lifts all boats, it will still widen the gap.

I don&#8217;t believe in planning too far for the future, but I always try to keep these trends in mind.

These ideas as a whole don&#8217;t paint a clear picture of the best path forwards. The concentration of wealth in those with capital suggests entrepreneurial careers or careers in leadership. The scientific revolutions that await us suggest deep study in rapidly advancing areas like biotechnology, computing, or energy. And the long lifespans we will enjoy suggests taking time off - after all, we have long working lives ahead of us.

You can&#8217;t ever optimize over everything, so picking the two trends you think are the most likely and will have the most influence on the future paints a clearer guiding path. If you believe science and the labor-capital divide are more relevant, that would direct you towards an entrepreneurial career in science. If you believe science and longer lifespans are more relevant, that would suggest a career in research - the academic path takes a long time, but you&#8217;ll live longer. And if you think longer lifespans and the labor-capital divide are more relevant, that suggests pursuing any relevant entrepreneurial or leadership career that you enjoy.

What do you think? Let me know!

### A crazier side note:

I am much, much less convinced of these things, but I foresee two outcomes for us over the next two centuries or so. Humanity reaches an unimaginably advanced level of technological achievement (exponential technological progress), or we end up killing ourselves off. This binary outcome is a fun thing to think about, but not anything that applies to decisions I make today.

<br>

<a name="1" href="#1-back">[1]</a> A microcosmic example of this is planning out college. Originally I carefully planned out all the classes I&#8217;d take during my four years at Berkeley. That plan was abandoned within my first year at Berkeley because I realized: 1) the professor teaching a class is the most important factor (and it changes every semester), 2) every semester I&#8217;d learn about a new topic I hadn&#8217;t been interested in before, and 3) new classes emerged every year.

<a name="2" href="#2-back">[2]</a> With hindsight we can notice the seeds of the fifty years that followed. Chemotherapy had barely emerged, and is today firmly established in medicine. African nations - independent - still struggle with the legacy of colonialism. And computing has exploded and taken over our lives.

<a name="3" href="#3-back">[3]</a> I have no idea if I&#8217;ll live to see *specific* technologies like artificial general intelligence or whatever else is going to be hyped tomorrow.

<a name="4" href="#4-back">[4]</a> [Income inequality in the United States](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Income_inequality_in_the_United_States). Income inequality *is* falling globally - but largely due to the catch-up development of the third world, where people are finding employment as inexpensive labor. Labor holds value in the third world, ironically contributing to the decline in labor&#8217;s share of wealth in America.
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Making Decisions]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.brianchu.com/blog/2014/03/28/making-decisions/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-28T08:22:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.brianchu.com/blog/2014/03/28/making-decisions</id>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="article-cover top-bottom-border" style="background-image: url('/images/blog/2014/decision-frameworks.jpg')"></div>

A few of the frameworks and factors I&#8217;ve encountered for thinking about the decisions and choices I make.

<!-- more -->

When facing multiple priorities and opportunities that you can take, consider these ideas:

1. **The regret-minimization framework:** Ask yourself which opportunity you will regret not taking. Ask yourself if you will regret doing something. This has probably been the most influential for me. <a name="1-back" href="#1">[1]</a>.

    Regret-minimization often helps me think about action versus inaction and risk versus safety. This can be mundane: should you go out to eat with friends or stay inside and eat by yourself? This can be a major life change: would you regret having worked at a startup? Or would you regret having stayed at a stable company? The answers to these questions can change depending on where you are in life. There are cases where you truly might regret going to a startup.

2. **Focus on optimizing a single factor and only then seek ways to mitigate the tradeoffs.** We tend to evaluate choices based on tradeoffs. <a name="2-back" href="#2">[2]</a>

    For example, an engineer friend of mine was trying to decide on which company to join. He felt that joining a rapidly growing startup would maximize his potential upside (through equity), whereas joining a big tech firm would give him the opportunity to learn more, earn him more money (expected value), and boost his resume. Staying at his current company would increase his opportunities for internal advancement. Under this framework, he should examine the most important factor (pick one of: education, salary, upside potential, advancement) to optimize, and ignore all other factors. This is useful because the most distracting part of making a decision is having to consider all of the tiny little tradeoffs that have to be evaluated.

3. **Consider which choices are time-dependent.**

    Some opportunities can only be seized now. An example would be a job offer about to expire. A subtler category of opportunities consists of opportunities that are *better* taken now, rather than later. For example, traveling is usually done better when you&#8217;re younger, because more activities and more social circles are open to you. But you can travel any time you&#8217;re physically fit. Similarly, attending college is usually better done when you&#8217;re younger, because of the people you meet and friendships you form, but you could still attend college at any point in life. Then there are opportunities that you have years and years to pursue in the future, like writing a book.

4. **Consider your comparative advantages.** Which opportunities are specific to your skills, and which are general opportunities open to all? You&#8217;re going to have a better chance of success pursuing an opportunity that suits your skills. I wrote more about this [in a previous blog post](/blog/2014/01/27/work-where-you-have-comparative-advantages/).

5. **Potential is greater than what is possible right now.** I try to refrain from judging opportunities by what they mean today. Judge them by what they mean for the future. This is more specifically geared towards technological opportunities.

    A relevant example is the recent trend of cryptocurrencies and Bitcoin. I personally don&#8217;t find Bitcoin to be very useful. I think it&#8217;s very flawed, and I&#8217;ve observed that most applications of cryptocurrencies seem like the result of engineers trying to come up with ideas for Bitcoin, rather than trying to solve actual problems with Bitcoin. But I try to stop myself from dismissing cryptocurrencies out of hand, simply because most flaws of cyptocurrencies are only flaws that exist today. They&#8217;re implementation flaws, not necessarily inherent flaws. These flaws might be eliminated in the future. A better cryptocurrency might arise. Better exchanges might arise. Brilliant and obviously useful applications of cryptocurrencies might arise. Potential is greater than what is possible today.

These are just ways of thinking about decisions, not hard rules on how to act. I don&#8217;t always follow these frameworks myself. Often these frameworks don&#8217;t apply. Sometimes they might even conflict!

<a name="1" href="#1-back">[1]</a> I encountered this in an [interview of Jeff Bezos](http://www.achievement.org/autodoc/page/bez0int-3).

<a name="2" href="#2-back">[2]</a> This was a piece of advice I read online, but I forget where I found it.]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Work where you have comparative advantages]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.brianchu.com/blog/2014/01/27/work-where-you-have-comparative-advantages/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-27T10:30:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.brianchu.com/blog/2014/01/27/work-where-you-have-comparative-advantages</id>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="article-cover" style="background-image: url('/images/blog/2014/comparative-advantage.jpg')"></div>

Like most developers, you probably keep a running list of ideas for apps you might build. I do. They all seem promising and potentially useful. How do you prioritize what to build? One way I try to decide what to work on: I think of my comparative advantages.

<!-- more -->

Work where you have a comparative advantage. Consider the unique skills, insights, networks of people, networks of beta users, and marketing channels that are available to you as a result of your where you are today and what you&#8217;ve done in the past. What you choose to work on should take advantage of those things <a name="1-back" href="#1">[1]</a>.

College students, like myself, will probably have greater insight into the social behavior of teenagers and twenty-somethings than other demographics <a name="2-back" href="#2">[2]</a>. They have access to an extremely broad and dense group of fellow students, all close to their age. They have access to college-specific activities - dorm life, taking classes, parties, homework - and close access to a set of potential beta users in a narrow demographic, other students. A college student can access a huge variety of college-specific marketing channels - friends, clubs, campus billboards, club tabling, and classes. An experienced engineer will have a different set comparative advantages. An engineer might have insight into the problems companies face with software architecture, databases, servers, testing. An engineer will have access to a strong network of engineers, managers, and CTOs. An engineer might have better access to other marketing channels - meetups, invite-only networking events, and technology conferences.

Domain expertise is a subset of comparative advantage. A college student would be hard-pressed to build a better CRM that takes the market. They don&#8217;t have domain expertise. On the other hand, an operations leader with years of enterprise experience would be hard-pressed to build the next trendy social networking app. They don&#8217;t have any domain expertise. They don&#8217;t necessarily suffer from handicaps; they just don&#8217;t have any legs up on the competition - twenty-somethings with the same ideas. So they would be better off competing elsewhere and exploiting their own comparative advantages.

Take a moment to think: what are your comparative advantages? What networks do you have access to, both as a result of your location and your experience? What skills do you have? What kind of beta users can you test your projects with? What insights do you have as a result of your experience? What other distribution/marketing channels do you have?

I&#8217;m in college right now (after a hiatus). That&#8217;s why my latest side project is tackling the problem of buying and selling things locally - a quintessentially college student problem.

*A cautionary note*: This is only one way to think about choosing your work. Working where you have comparative advantages can sometimes conflict with other valuable goals. Examples include: trying becoming well-rounded, trying to change careers, and trying to learn about new technologies. In those cases you have to take other factors into account!

<a name="1" href="#1-back">[1]</a> I don&#8217;t use the term as precisely as it&#8217;s used in economics. Technically, comparative advantage is the idea that economies are better at producing different goods. Perhaps China produces cars more efficiently than software. Perhaps America produces software more efficiently than cars. Even if America is more efficient in absolute terms at mass-producing cars than China, the idea behind comparative advantage is that if America focuses on software, China focuses on cars, and both trade with each other, both will be richer than if they didn&#8217;t focus on their comparative advantages.

<a name="2" href="#2-back">[2]</a> I use the term &#8220;probably&#8221; very loosely, on the assumption that &#8220;you get the point.&#8221; None of these are absolutes. There are definitely college students who don&#8217;t know anything about their fellow students. There are definitely people 10 years out of school that have deep insight into teenage social behavior.]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
