<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Product Thoughts | I'm Brian Chu]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.brianchu.com/blog/categories/product-thoughts/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.brianchu.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-28T07:35:14-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.brianchu.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brian Chu]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Photo Embarrassment]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.brianchu.com/blog/2013/09/11/photo-embarrassment/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-11T10:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.brianchu.com/blog/2013/09/11/photo-embarrassment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Instagram and Snapchat seem to share a common theme: they try to solve the hurdle of photo embarrassment &ndash; they find ways to get around our self-restraint with sharing photos. <!-- more --> Instagram does this with filters so that users can create beautiful pictures of mundane scenes. Snapchat does this with ephemeral photos that disappear[1].</p>

<p>This theme fits in with my observations of frequent users of Instagram and Snapchat. Instagram photos seems to lean towards the aspirational and idealized &ndash; an expression of a desired identity. I see my friends posting idealized pictures of food, activities, moments, scenery, and people. Filters get users to share photos of mundane moments when they would otherwise exercise self-restraint.</p>

<p>Snapchat seems to lean towards reality and the moment &ndash; a way of communicating your current status. I have friends that just post pictures of their faces (very specifically and almost exclusively their faces) throughout the day. Snapchat has in that sense become Twitter for photos: the disappearance of photos is not a gimmick but just a way to get users to take and share unflattering photos of themselves (the unflattering photo seems to be the hallmark of a Snapchat photo), when they would otherwise exercise self-restraint.</p>

<p>[1] The fact that Snapchat does not have any technology that will actually ensure a photo&rsquo;s disappearance is largely irrelevant, for the same reason that it&rsquo;s irrelevant that Instagram does not guarantee your photos will actually look good.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
