<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: product thoughts | I'm Brian Chu]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.brianchu.com/blog/categories/product-thoughts/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.brianchu.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-09-25T14:29:51-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.brianchu.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brian Chu]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Work where you have comparative advantages]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.brianchu.com/blog/2014/01/27/work-where-you-have-comparative-advantages/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-27T10:30:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.brianchu.com/blog/2014/01/27/work-where-you-have-comparative-advantages</id>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="article-cover" style="background-image: url('/images/blog/2014/comparative-advantage.jpg')"></div>

Like most developers, you probably keep a running list of ideas for apps you might build. I do. They all seem promising and potentially useful. How do you prioritize what to build? One way I try to decide what to work on: I think of my comparative advantages.

<!-- more -->

Work where you have a comparative advantage. Consider the unique skills, insights, networks of people, networks of beta users, and marketing channels that are available to you as a result of your where you are today and what you&#8217;ve done in the past. What you choose to work on should take advantage of those things <a name="1-back" href="#1">[1]</a>.

College students, like myself, will probably have greater insight into the social behavior of teenagers and twenty-somethings than other demographics <a name="2-back" href="#2">[2]</a>. They have access to an extremely broad and dense group of fellow students, all close to their age. They have access to college-specific activities - dorm life, taking classes, parties, homework - and close access to a set of potential beta users in a narrow demographic, other students. A college student can access a huge variety of college-specific marketing channels - friends, clubs, campus billboards, club tabling, and classes. An experienced engineer will have a different set comparative advantages. An engineer might have insight into the problems companies face with software architecture, databases, servers, testing. An engineer will have access to a strong network of engineers, managers, and CTOs. An engineer might have better access to other marketing channels - meetups, invite-only networking events, and technology conferences.

Domain expertise is a subset of comparative advantage. A college student would be hard-pressed to build a better CRM that takes the market. They don&#8217;t have domain expertise. On the other hand, an operations leader with years of enterprise experience would be hard-pressed to build the next trendy social networking app. They don&#8217;t have any domain expertise. They don&#8217;t necessarily suffer from handicaps; they just don&#8217;t have any legs up on the competition - twenty-somethings with the same ideas. So they would be better off competing elsewhere and exploiting their own comparative advantages.

Take a moment to think: what are your comparative advantages? What networks do you have access to, both as a result of your location and your experience? What skills do you have? What kind of beta users can you test your projects with? What insights do you have as a result of your experience? What other distribution/marketing channels do you have?

I&#8217;m in college right now (after a hiatus). That&#8217;s why my latest side project is tackling the problem of buying and selling things locally - a quintessentially college student problem.

*A cautionary note*: This is only one way to think about choosing your work. Working where you have comparative advantages can sometimes conflict with other valuable goals. Examples include: trying becoming well-rounded, trying to change careers, and trying to learn about new technologies. In those cases you have to take other factors into account!

<a name="1" href="#1-back">[1]</a> I don&#8217;t use the term as precisely as it&#8217;s used in economics. Technically, comparative advantage is the idea that economies are better at producing different goods. Perhaps China produces cars more efficiently than software. Perhaps America produces software more efficiently than cars. Even if America is more efficient in absolute terms at mass-producing cars than China, the idea behind comparative advantage is that if America focuses on software, China focuses on cars, and both trade with each other, both will be richer than if they didn&#8217;t focus on their comparative advantages.

<a name="2" href="#2-back">[2]</a> I use the term &#8220;probably&#8221; very loosely, on the assumption that &#8220;you get the point.&#8221; None of these are absolutes. There are definitely college students who don&#8217;t know anything about their fellow students. There are definitely people 10 years out of school that have deep insight into teenage social behavior.]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Photo Embarrassment]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.brianchu.com/blog/2013/09/11/photo-embarrassment/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-11T10:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.brianchu.com/blog/2013/09/11/photo-embarrassment</id>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[Instagram and Snapchat seem to share a common theme: they try to solve the hurdle of photo embarrassment - they find ways to get around our self-restraint with sharing photos. <!-- more --> Instagram does this with filters so that users can create beautiful pictures of mundane scenes. Snapchat does this with ephemeral photos that disappear <a name="1-back" href="#1">[1]</a>.

This theme fits in with my observations of frequent users of Instagram and Snapchat. Instagram photos seems to lean towards the aspirational and idealized - an expression of a desired identity. I see my friends posting idealized pictures of food, activities, moments, scenery, and people. Filters get users to share photos of mundane moments when they would otherwise exercise self-restraint.

Snapchat seems to lean towards reality and the moment - a way of communicating your current status. I have friends that just post pictures of their faces (very specifically and almost exclusively their faces) throughout the day. Snapchat has in that sense become Twitter for photos: the disappearance of photos is not a gimmick but just a way to get users to take and share unflattering photos of themselves (the unflattering photo seems to be the hallmark of a Snapchat photo), when they would otherwise exercise self-restraint.

<a name="1" href="#1-back">[1]</a> The fact that Snapchat does not have any technology that will actually ensure a photo&#8217;s disappearance is largely irrelevant, for the same reason that it&#8217;s irrelevant that Instagram does not guarantee your photos will actually look good.]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
